All
right.
Good morning. Good morning. It's still start... there we go. Okay, so
we're going to start at the משנה Mishna at the bottom of
דף צ"ח עמוד ב'. Daf Tzadik Chet Amud Bet. We saw this
משנה Mishna a couple of chapters ago when it got brought in
by the גמרא Gemara in a discussion of a craftsman who's finished
his work and says come get it and pay me what I'm
due, which is actually the last time I was the one teaching.
But here we're just seeing it in its own context.
It's חזרה Chazarah for you. It's חזרה, Chazarah, yeah.
So the משנה Mishna starts: השואל את הפרה ושלחה לו ביד בנו
ביד עבדו ביד שלוחו או ביד בנו ביד עבדו ביד שלוחו של
שואל ומתה פטור.
Hashoel Et HaPara V'Shlachah Lo
B'Yad Beno, B'Yad Avdo, B'Yad Shlucho, O B'Yad Beno, B'Yad Avdo, B'Yad
Shlucho Shel Shoel U'Metah Patur. So if I borrow somebody's cow, somebody
borrows their friend's cow, and the owner of the cow sends it
by way of his son or his slave or an agent, or
by way of the son or the slave or the agent of
the person who's borrowing it, and it dies on the way to
the hands of the person who's borrowing it, the person who's borrowing
it is פטור. Patur. Normally, a person who's borrowing it is the
most liable for keeping guard of an object that's in their possession
that belongs to another person.
They're obligated for everything including אונסים, Onsim, so something that happens to
the object,
just what anything that happens to the object, object is lost, object's
stolen, object is destroyed, even if it's not their fault, even if
it's not פשיעה, Peshiah, they didn't make an error, they didn't do
something wrong in their guardianship, they're still liable for the damages,
unlike a שוכר Socher or a שומר שכר Shomer Sachar or a
שומר חנם Shomer Chinam who have lower levels of obligation for the
objects they're guarding. That's someone who's renting an object, someone who's being
paid to guard the object, or someone who's just guarding the object
for free, they have lower levels of obligation, as we've talked about
before. So in this case, in this case, he has a high
level of obligation, nonetheless he's פטור Patur here because it hasn't yet
come to his hand. If it's still in the hands of the
people bringing it to him and it hasn't left the רשות, Reshut,
it hasn't left the domain, legal domain of the owner of the
object, then the borrower is not yet liable for אונסים, Onsim, is
not yet liable for something that happens to it.
This is a case where the borrower didn't ask it to be
sent this way, correct?
And in the bottom, borrower, if I
ask you to send it, then I am חייב. Chayav.
If I ask you to... okay. אמר לו השואל Amar Lo HaShoel
שלחה לו ביד בני ביד עבדי ביד שלוחי או ביד בנך ביד
עבדך ביד שלוחך, Shlachah Lo B'Yad Beni, B'Yad Avdi, B'Yad Shluchi, O
B'Yad Bincha, B'Yad Avdecha, B'Yad Shluchecha, so if the borrower says, send
it by way of my son, my slave, or my agent,
או שאמר לו המשאיל, O She'Amar Lo HaMashil, or if
the lender
says, הריני משלח לך ביד בני ביד עבדי ביד שלוחי או ביד
בנך ביד עבדך ביד שלוחך, Hareini Meshaleach Lach B'Yad Beni, B'Yad Avdi,
B'Yad Shluchi, O B'Yad Bincha, B'Yad Avdecha, B'Yad Shluchecha, your son, your
slave, or agent, and the שואל Shoel says, אמר לו השואל שלח,
Amar Lo HaShoel Shlach, okay, send it, ושלחה ומתה חייב, V'shlachah U'Metah
Chayav, because at that point he's obligated, because it already entered into
his legal רשות. Reshut. וכן בשעה שמחזירה, V'Chen Be'Sha'ah She'Machzirah, the same
rule applies, as we saw before a number of weeks ago when
the object is being returned, that it depends on if I'm returning
it to you in a way that I decided, then I'm חייב
Chayav until it gets to the owner's hand. And if I'm doing
it in a way that we've decided on together, or in a
way that you told me to do it, then you're obligated once
it leaves my physical hand, once it leaves my physical hands,
even if it's going by the way of my slave.
Then we also see that depends if the term was up or
not?
That's what we said last time, but that's not what we're talking
about here. Now we're talking about the issue of a slave, and
that's where the גמרא Gemara picks up. ביד עבדו חייב. B'Yad Avdo
Chayav. Wait, why is that the case? Why is it the case
that when I send it by the hand of my slave to
you,
that I'm חייב Chayav until it gets to you, or not my
slave, your slave. Isn't יד עבד כיד רבו? Yad Eved K'Yad Rabo?
Isn't the slave treated as
כאילו Ke-illu that the master is actually there?
אמר שמואל בעבד עברי דלא קני לגופיה. Amar Shmuel B'Eved Ivri D'Lo
Kani L'Gufeh. Oh, here we have a simple answer that שמואל Shmuel
gives. We're not talking about an עבד כנעני Eved Knaani who's actually
יד עבד כיד רבו Yad Eved K'Yad Rabo almost ממש, Mamash, that
we actually treat the person as if the owner is there because
his גוף Guf is קנוי, Kanuy, because his body is owned by
the owner. Here we're talking about עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, we're talking
about a Hebrew slave
who's owned a much lower level of ownership and so we don't
say יד עבד כיד רבו, Yad Eved K'Yad Rabo, we don't treat
it as if the master is there as well, and so thus
there is no problem in the משנה Mishna in the משנה. Mishna.
רב
אמר,
Rav
Amar, רב Rav has a different answer. אפילו תימא בעבד כנעני, Afillu
Teima B'Eved Knaani, we can even say it's about עבד כנעני, Eved
Knaani, we can even say it's about the non-Jewish person who's a
slave who is entirely owned by the master.
נעשה כאומר לו הכישהו במקל ויבא. Na'aseh Ke'Omer Lo Hakhishehu B'Makel V'Yavo.
No, we treat that case where it's sent... Sent by way of
the עבד כנעני eved Cana'ani as if we're talking about return in
this case, as if the owner says hit it with the stick
and it'll come.
We're not really talking about the owner, we're going to switch back
to talking about the borrower, but it's at the point of borrowing
that when it's sent by the hand of the עבד כנעני, eved
Cana'ani,
it's treated as if it's that the act of משיכה. meshicha. I'll
also explain what that means in a second, that
if
I tell you hit the animal and it comes, that's a קנין,
kinyan, that's a formal act of acquisition because I can't,
because normally with objects that are movable I have to take possession
of them through משיכה, meshicha, pulling them towards me, moving them from
one place to another. With an animal because I can't actually physically
move the animal, one way of doing that is to hit it
and it'll come to me. Not hit it particularly hard, but enough
that it'll move by my action. So here an עבד כנעני eved
Cana'ani is treated as if it's an act of קנין, kinyan, an
act of משיכה. meshicha. Alternatively, that they think the עבד כנעני eved
Cana'ani is treated because he's גופו קנוי, gufo kanui, because it's entirely
the possession of the owner, he's entirely the possession of the owner,
excuse me. It's treated as if there are sort of two objects
owned by the master and so when one does to the other
when one does something it's as if just the animal itself moved
because we don't treat it entirely like a person doing
it.
Okay. אתי שפיר. Ati shapir. אתי שפיר? Ati shapir? ביד עבדו הוא
דחייב? B'yad avdo hu d'chayav? What's the exact, what's the קשיא? kashya?
רש"י Rashi is בתמיה, bitmiya, right? Yes.
So the קשיא, kashya,
פשיטא, pshita, is the קשיא kashya like it was פשיטא pshita there?
If I'm so, if I'm sending it, if I'm loaning you my
cow and I own a non-Jewish slave and I send it to
you by way of my non-Jewish slave, it hasn't left my hand.
יד עבד כיד רבו. Yad eved k'yad rabo. If my slave is
moving something, is moving something for me, it is as if I'm
moving it. Right. So how is it possible to ever say that
it's passed out of my possession?
That's the question.
שמואל Shmuel answers that oh, we're not dealing with an עבד כנעני
eved Cana'ani
where it's כאילו k'ilu it's me. We're dealing with another Jewish person
who's in my, who's my slave but then it's not me doing
it. But רב Rav says no, we can even say עבד כנעני
eved Cana'ani because it's as if I hit it and it went
to you and you did the formal act of acquisition occurred in
is the same as the עבד כנעני eved Cana'ani bringing it to
you. And so that's how it's חייב. chayav. But this is also,
this is problematic. מיתיבי. Meitivei. It's problematic, we have a question. השואל
פרה ושילחה לו ביד בנו ביד שלוחו חייב ביד עבדו פטור.
Hasho'el para v'shilchah lo b'yad bno b'yad
shlucho chayav b'yad avdo patur. There's another ברייתא braita that actually brings
up this issue, that not every עבד eved is the, that there's
another ברייתא braita that disagrees with the משנה mishna that when we
say עבד eved we say פטור patur just like the הוה אמינא
hava amina of the גמרא gemara
that we had the question how's it possible that the slave bringing
it could ever make the borrower liable
and the answer is it's not according to this ברייתא. braita. Now
we have to square that with our two אמוראים. Amoraim. One way
is easy. בשלמא לשמואל מתניתין בעבד עברי ברייתא בעבד כנעני. Bishlama l'Shmuel
matnitin b'eved Ivri braita b'eved Cana'ani.
That's easy for שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel can say
the משנה mishna is talking about an עבד עברי. eved Ivri. When
the משנה mishna says ביד עבדו חייב, b'yad avdo chayav, sending it
by way of the slave the borrower is liable, because we're talking
about a Jewish slave. That's fine. And the ברייתא braita is talking
about עבד כנעני eved Cana'ani and so he's פטור. patur. So then
that when the owner sends it by way of a non-Jewish slave,
the borrower is not liable for damages until it actually reaches him.
אלא לרב קשיא. Ela l'Rav kashya.
But it's a problem for רב. Rav. How can רב Rav who
says אפילו לעבד כנעני נעשה כאומר ליה הכישה במקלא והיא תבא?
afilu l'eved Cana'ani na'aseh k'omeir lei hakishei b'makla
v'hi tavo?
How can he say that we treat that the עבד כנעני eved
Cana'ani bringing it is an act of formal acquisition? How can he
have one source that says חייב chayav and one source that says
פטור? patur? אמר לך רב לא תימא נעשה כאומר ליה אלא אימא
באמר ליה הכישה במקלא והיא תבא.
Amar lach Rav lo teima
na'aseh k'omeir lei ela eima b'amar lei hakishei b'makla v'hi tavo. No,
we make this,
we make the problematic source say that
not that when I said נעשה, na'aseh, I didn't mean נעשה. na'aseh.
We don't mean, I don't mean that we treat it as if.
I say we actually have to fix the משנה mishna I
think and say מוקמינן לה. mokminan lah. The משנה mishna when I
say the משנה mishna is נעשה na'aseh I don't mean that we
treat the case as if, we say no, that's a case where
he actually said it. So when the משנה mishna says ביד עבדו
חייב, b'yad avdo chayav,
he actually said הכישה במקלא והיא תבא, hakishei b'makla v'hi tavo, hit
the animal so it'll come to me and instead of doing that
he sent it with the עבד כנעני. eved Cana'ani. And so those
are treated as the same. But if I say send it to
me and he sends it by way of the עבד כנעני, eved
Cana'ani, that's still פטור. patur. That's a lower level of obligation for
the borrower. אלא
אימא באמר ליה הכישה
במקלא והיא
תבא דאיתמר. Ela eima b'amar lei hakishei b'makla v'hi tavo d'itmar. Because
we have a source that says the same thing. השאילני פרתך hashileni
paratcha ואמר ליה ve'amar leh בידי beyadi ואמר ליה ve'amar leh הקישה
במקלו והיא תבוא, hekishah bimaklo vehi tavo, מקל תבוא makal tavo ותבוא
vetavo ותבוא. vetavo. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב
amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha
amar Rav
because we have the source that says that talks about this case
of if I say, lend me your cow, and I say and
the owner says, how should I send it, בידי, beyadi, ואמר ליה
ve'amar leh הקישה במקלו והיא תבוא. hekishah bimaklo vehi tavo. אמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוּה אמר רב, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha amar Rav, כיון שיצאת מרשות משאיל מתה חייב kevan sheyatzat
mereshut mash'il metah chayav because in that case where I said literally
hit the animal with a stick and it will come to me,
that's passed into my
רשות. reshut. נימא מסייע ליה: neima mesayei leh: השאילני פרתך hashileni paratcha
ואמר ליה ve'amar leh בידי beyadi ואמר ליה ve'amar leh הקישה במקלו
והיא תבוא, hekishah bimaklo vehi tavo, כיון שיצאת מרשות משאיל מתה חייב.
kevan sheyatzat mereshut mash'il metah chayav.
Should we say that this is a help for him, that this
is help for רבא? Rava? We have the source that says this
for רב. Rav. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, no, this source
actually can't help רב. Rav. רב אשי Rav Ashi finds רב'ס Rav's
answer problematic. See why. הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, in this
source, כגון שהייתה חצר של שואל לפנים מחצר של משאיל, kegon shehayetah
chatzer shel sho'el lifnim michatzer shel mash'il, דכיון דנפקה אבדה לה התם
אזלה. dekevan denafkah avdah lah hatam azlah. Ah,
רב אשי Rav Ashi says the ברייתא braita can't really be used
as a support for רב Rav because it's actually talking about a
very specific case. The specific case is when we have the
שואל'ס חצר sho'el's chatzer is לפנים lifnim within the משאיל'ס חצר. mash'il's
chatzer.
Yes.
Now, that might be silly, it's like why am I living inside
the חצר chatzer of somebody else, but
לפנים lifnim means in inside,
it does mean inside of.
So like we have like it's a big courtyard is a big
courtyard and inside that big courtyard is a smaller domain and that's
the domain of the שואל. sho'el. לפנים, lifnim, I think there means
inside.
Yep, it does mean inside. So the point is is that when
I say as a borrower, hit it to me, hit it and
send it to me, I know that it's going to come to
me because there's nowhere else that it's going to go.
רש"י Rashi explains it doesn't have to go through a רשות הרבים
reshut harabim in the in between. If it has to go through
a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, I don't know where it's going to
end up going if you're just sending the animal and that's the
act of that's the act of קנין, kinyan, that's the act of
acquisition.
Now
okay, רב אשי Rav Ashi made the ברייתא braita problematic for רב,
Rav, but in the ברייתא braita doesn't teach us anything new apparently.
אי הכי מאי למימרא? ei hachi mai lemimra? לא צריכא דאיכא גזייתא,
lo tzericha de'ika gezyata, מהו דתימא לא סמכה דעתיה דילמא קיימא התם
ולא אתיא להדיא, mahu deteima lo samcha da'ateih dilma kayama hatam velo
atya lehadi, קא משמע לן דסמכה דעתיה. ka mashma lan desamcha da'ateih.
No, so
what's what's the new teaching in this ברייתא braita about where the
חצר של שואל chatzer shel sho'el is
לפנים מחצר של משאיל? lifnim michatzer shel mash'il? That we're talking about
a space within the owner's space that it's like I'm not just
borrowing the cow from its owner, I'm also the
I'm also
while I own space within the other person's space, I'm leasing space
from my from my landlord and then I'm borrowing the cow from
him, I live within his
חצר. chatzer.
So in a way it means if the cow never leaves the
רשות reshut of the owner.
Ah,
not quite. If that's the case if we're talking about borrowing renting
that, but that's not necessarily what we're talking about we're talking about
owning space, okay, strangely proportioned space. I understand. But so how are
how are we dealing with the ברייתא? braita? The ברייתא braita is
dealing with what if there are intermediate places within the רשות, reshut,
within the private domain, that it could have gone? So like let's
say a big חצר, chatzer, it's
interstitial space.
Yeah,
big חצר, chatzer, we're going to pretend that there's walls, filled in
walls. Here's my חצר chatzer and my entrance, the cow's over here
look pretty cow, right? Look at all the lines. Okay, but then
somebody else has space over here.
And so you're saying it's going to go over here, but it
might also go over there, it might also go over here.
We don't know where quite where it's going to go but we
know there's no רשות הרבים reshut harabim in the in between according
to רש"י. Rashi.
And so that's how the ברייתא braita teaches us something new.
ראב"ד Ra'avad says it slightly differently, we just add something. The ראב"ד
Ra'avad in the שיטה מקובצת Shitta Mekubetzet says that when we're talking
about the חצר שמלפנים, chatzer shemilifnim, it's דוקא davka that the borrower's
space is within the space is within the larger חצר chatzer of
the owner's space. Because if it were the opposite, we can't have
the same assumption about what I mean. So if I live here
and I'm borrowing your cow from the big חצר chatzer and you're
sending it into my space, that's weird that you're sending my cow
into my space and when I say send it to me,
I mean send it to me means you're lending it to me.
But if this is your space and you own the cow and
you're sending it into my space, to get out to the street
you have to go through my space all the time. So it's
not strictly not exactly meaningful for you to move your cow into
my space.
Why not? I mean, I told you to do it, you know,
the the meaning depends on the context.
Ah, but maybe I'm moving Ah, but maybe I'm moving it somewhere
else.
I'm telling you to move it to me.
Right, but so then since you tell me to move it to
you, I can't take my cow out anymore without lending it to
you?
No, no, I mean, granted if I gave you, if you normally
have rights to do it, then it means nothing, but if I
tell you specifically to do it, then it changes everything. But if
I take that coffee thing of yours, if you didn't let me
do it, I'm stealing it. If you let me do it, I'm
borrowing it. It's totally different.
No, you're wanting to borrow my cow. Correct. So I have to
be able to, I have to have a choice of whether I
want you to borrow my cow or not. If I say let
me borrow your cow by sending it out into the main space,
then I'm like, oh I don't want to do that, I just
want to take my cow for a walk.
Fine, then I don't get to borrow it.
But I'm doing the thing that you're saying to do in order
to borrow it.
No, but it depends on whether in that context or not. I
mean, am I allowed to borrow it, or you're just not, you're
just not doing this specifically to send it to me?
What am I not getting? The point is is that it's not
quite the same. If I'm living within the, if I'm living within
your domain. Right. And I'm borrowing your cow and I say send
it to me, and by hitting it, by pushing it, by putting
it in itself, and that we're saying that that makes me חייב
chayav once you push it, like it's not even in my חצר
chatzer yet, it's over here still in your חצר chatzer but you've
hit it to send it to me. Right. I have enough of
an assumption that it's going to come to me and that's going
once it passes into mine, then even when it's not in my
space which I erased, it's already my חיוב chiyuv in case somebody
comes and whacks it.
That's different, we can't have the same assumption says the ראב"ד Raivad
if you live here and I live here, because pushing your cow
into my space is not the same, is basically pushing your cow
into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
מסתמא, mistama, from the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and the חצר? chatzer?
That's that's the ראב"ד's Raivad claim because I constantly move my cow
into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
But
it's not a רשות הרבים reshut harabbim yet.
No, but moving it out into your חצר chatzer is not the
same, is not the same when you're moving into the outer חצר
chatzer because it's towards the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. We're now combining
רש"י Rashi and ראב"ד, Raivad, but we're going to need to move
on.
It's multiple, it's multiple things that it could mean. Yeah, it's confusing
what it means.
הכא במאי עסקינן במחטל? Hacha b'mai askinan b'machtal? If, if... that's why
I differentiated... הכא במאי עסקינן במחטל... Hacha b'mai askinan b'machtal... yeah... and
the owner comes... so and it stays
under the owner's supervision. Does that mean...
I think that that's פטור patur because the owner is, these are
only talking about the cases where it's brought by somebody else's hand
where we could actually treat it as if the owner is there.
יד עבד כיד רבו, Yad eved k'yad rabbo, the child of the
of the master is sometimes treated as the master, and the and
שליח shaliach
and
שליח shaliach is also treated like the master. Right. And so all
of those cases are intermediate ones where we could say the master
is there, we could say the master is not there. And so
it depends on the context. If the master is literally there, no
matter what I told you, if I'm still here, then you can't
be חייב chayav for the thing that I'm with.
Is that because בעליו עמו? be'alav imo? Hmm? Yes. That's because בעליו
עמו. be'alav imo. I would think so.
I'm assuming, I'm extrapolating from this, I don't know that for a
hundred percent, but that would be clear to me from the way
this is talking about these things. Okay. And now apparently we move
from questions of borrowing to questions of הקדש hekdesh or we bring
הקדש hekdesh into the mix.
אמר הונא. Amar Huna. הונא Huna says, השואל קרדום מחבירו, Hashoel kardom
mechaveiro, so I borrow an axe from my friend. בקע בו קנאו
לא בקע בו לא קנאו. Baka bo kenao lo baka bo lo
kenao. Okay, if I borrow an axe from you, I haven't really
acquired it until I've used it. Fine.
Since when? If I if I take it from your hand and
I walk with it four אמות, amot, I haven't acquired it?
Not for שאילה. sheilah. No, that's what it says.
Why? We say the משיכה. meshichah. So if I want to borrow
your mixer, I have to like, you know, mix with it? If
I want to borrow your whatever, your car, I have to drive
it, you know? Because... oh, so here... that's when you give me
the keys?
Because דקסבר dekasvar says רש"י, Rashi, אין משיכה קונה בשומרים, ein meshichah
konah b'shomrim, that actually taking the the normal taking possession...
Wait, what are you...
oh, you're looking at רש"י? Rashi?
Yes. דיבור המתחיל Dibur hamatchil לא בקע בו לא קנאו, lo baka
bo lo kenao, דקסבר dekasvar אין משיכה קונה בשומרים ein meshichah konah
b'shomrim that when I'm just a שומר, shomer, when I'm a שואל
shoel who's a kind of שומר, shomer, if I'm a borrower who's
a kind of guardian of it, then the simple act the normal
formal act of taking possession of a movable object doesn't create the
חיוב chiyuv of a שומר, shomer, it doesn't make me the guardian
such that I would be obligated for damage to the object.
Then what does? Just using it? Just using it. No, but שומר
חנם shomer chinam I can't use it.
שומר חנם Shomer chinam that's different. שומר חנם Shomer chinam also has
a very low level of liability.
No, but he's saying בשומרים, b'shomrim, it just means, he means
any שומר shomer he's saying.
But really, but we're going to see...
This is רש"י's Rashi also setting us up for the end where
we conclude that there is משיכה meshichah by שומר. shomer. Okay, well
so
I'm so I'm sorry.
So if I'm שומר חנם shomer chinam which I can't use it,
so I still have to pull it in?
All right. Let's go to, we read the next, maybe it's going
to make the same argument you're making. Okay. לא קנאו למאי? Lo
kenao lemai? אילימא לאונסין, Eilima l'onsin, מאי שנא... mai shna...
מה שנא פר דמשעת שאילה *ma shena par mishat sheila* אלא לחזרה
*ela l'chazara*? So what does this really, what does this really mean
what it says? If it means that I’m חייב chayav *chayav* for
אונסין *onsin* as I was explaining it a moment ago, why should
it be different from the פרה *para*? That from the moment that
I take it, from the moment of משיכה *meshikha*, from the moment
of the formal acquisition, which in the case of the פרה *para*
was hitting it so that it will come.
Why should it be different? I should take it, says Michael, and
it should be mine in order that I should be liable for
any damages that occur to it.
No, it's not about אונסין *onsin*, אלא לחזרה *ela l'chazara*. It's about
whether I can renege on the deal to borrow it. ובקבו לא
מצי הדבר משאיל *uvakavo lo matzi hadavar mash'il*.
If I’ve already used it, you can't say, no, no, no, you're
not allowed to borrow it. But I already used it, I'm already
the שואל *sho'el*. We said I could have this for a week
and you tell me that I can't? I need this. לא
בקבו מצי משאיל הדר
ביה *lo bakavo matzi mash'il hadar beih*. If I haven't yet used
it, you can say, you know what? I changed my mind. You
can't have my axe. Give me my axe back. Go find another
axe. ופליגא דרבי אמי *upliga d'Rabbi Ami*. Now רב הונא *Rav Huna*
has this opinion that it, that משיכה *meshikha* doesn't work to create
the חיוב אונסין *chiyuv onsin*. That the formal act of acquisition doesn't
work to create my liability for damages to the object when I'm
in my guardianship.
But other people do think that it has that. פליגא
דרבי אמי דאמר רבי
אמי המשאיל קרדום של הקדש hekdesh, מעל לפי טובת הנאה hana'ah שבו
וחברו מותר לבקבו לכתחילה *pliga d'Rabbi Ami d'amar Rabbi Ami hamash'il kardom
shel hekdesh ma'al lefi tovat hana'ah shebo vachavero mutar levakavo l'chatchila*.
Rabbi Ami says if you, Michael, have a הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* axe,
you have an axe that’s dedicated to the temple property
and you lend it to me, you're חייב chayav *chayav* in מעילה
me'ilah. *me'ila*, you're חייב *chayav* for the misappropriation of the temple property
לפי הנאתו *lefi hana'ato* according to the amount of benefit that you
get from lending it, which is a very small amount, that what
you would pay to be able to have an axe to lend.
And I'm allowed to use it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*.
Because
once it's the
second, once it's the second point, then I'm not חייב *chayav* for
מעילה me'ilah *me'ila*.
Wait, say that again?
You have an axe that belongs to the temple. You מקדיש *makdish*
the axe. You lend it to me. Right. You're חייב *chayav* in
מעילה me'ilah *me'ila*. It's a very small liability because you're not actually
using the axe. You're חייב *chayav* only for the amount that you
would pay to have an axe to lend. That's לפי הנאתו *lefi
hana'ato*.
Which means what? That means if I would pay a dollar, means
I have to pay the dollar and then a חומש chomesh, *chomesh*
back? Yes. Okay, me too.
Okay. But I'm allowed to use it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*. ואי לא קנה
אמאי amai מעל *ve'i lo kana amai ma'al*? But if I haven't
acquired it through the משיכה *meshikha*, if I haven't acquired it through
just taking it from you, I never said that I used the
axe yet, then how is there מעילה me'ilah. *me'ila*? Why are you
חייב *chayav* in מעילה me'ilah *me'ila*?
ואמאי חברו מותר לבקבו
לכתחילה נהדריה ולא ליקני ולא לימעול *ve'amai chavero mutar levakavo l'chatchila nehadreih
v'lo liknei v'lo lim'ol*?
If that's the case, then I should, if it's the case that
משיכה *meshikha* doesn't work, if it's the case that the act of
acquisition of taking the axe doesn't work to move it into my
possession such that I could use it לכתחילה *l'chatchila* and the owner
of the axe and the owner, so to speak, the person who
was in possession of the הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh* axe has to pay
the temple back for the misappropriation of it, then if it's the
case that the משיכה *meshikha* doesn't work, then I should just return
it to him and no one should be חייב *chayav* in מעילה
me'ilah *me'ila*.
Yeah, because it never left his רשות *reshut*, so to speak.
But because it, but Rabbi Ami holds it did leave his רשות
*reshut*. That משיכה *meshikha* is קונה *koneh* by לוקחין *lokchin*, משיכה *meshikha*
is קונה *koneh* by שומרים *shomrim*, that this act, that this act
of acquisition works to create a חיוב *chiyuv* even on a דאורייתא
*d'oraita* level such that before I've ever used the axe, he's חייב
*chayav* on מעילה me'ilah *me'ila* for lending the axe out.
So what did the תלמוד *Talmud* deal with the relationship between שמירה
*shmira* and קנין *kinyan*?
Yes, when what kind of קנין *kinyan* is needed to create
the שמירה *shmira*?
Right. Right. And underneath that is the assumption you need some concept
of קנין *kinyan* in order to effect the legal status of שמירה
*shmira*.
Right. Remember we also saw this last time when we were talking
about what does it have to be if you're leaving something with
me. Is it הונח לפני *hunach lefanai*? Is it הונח *hunach*?
Is that enough?
We said that there's a relatively high level for a שומר חנם
*shomer chinam* of what I have to say to put myself even
onto the level of a שומר חנם *shomer chinam*, which is a
low level of
obligation,
a low level of liability.
So the foundational concept to create some level of שמירה *shmira* is
some aspect of קנין *kinyan*.
Right. So Rabbi Ami disagrees with רב הונא *Rav Huna*. רב הונא
*Rav Huna* says the קנין *kinyan* that works is use.
Rabbi Ami says אפילו מדאורייתא *afilu mid'oraita* the formal קנין *kinyan* of
taking works and ופליגא דרבי אלעזר *upliga d'Rabbi Elazar*. Rabbi Elazar says
it's going to work דרבנן *derabbanan*. דאמר רבי אלעזר כדרך שתיקנו משיכה
בלקוחות כך תיקנו משיכה בשומרים *damar Rabbi Elazar kederech shetiknu meshikha belakochot
kach tiknu meshikha beshomrim*. That in fact, the way we, that in
fact
taking an object without using it makes me the שומר *shomer* of
it. That is enough to create to finish the to finish the
lending that makes me the current borrower of the object. מית *meis*,
if it's an if it's an if it's an object of הקדש
hekdesh, *hekdesh*, it makes the person who is holding the הקדש hekdesh.
*hekdesh* object liable for loaning it out. But this is only מדרבנן
*mi'derabbanan* שתיקנו *she'tichnu*, they they were מתקן *metaken* this rule. The חז"ל
*Chazal* made the rule that if I do the formal act of
acquisition, that works. תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi*, we also have
a ברייתא *beraita* that says this: כשם שתיקנו משיכה בלקוחות כך תיקנו
משיכה בשומרים *keshem shetiknu meshicha belokochot kach tiknu meshicha beshomrim* וכשם שקרקע
נקנית בכסף בשטר ובחזקה כך שכירות נקנית בכסף בשטר ובחזקה *ucheshem shekarka
nikne b'kesef b'shtar u'v'chazaka kach schirus nikne b'kesef b'shtar u'v'chazaka*. Just as
buying land works through
money, contracts, and חזקה *chazaka*, which is that I have the person
I'm actually on the land and it looks like I'm the owner
and I'm acting like the owner, כך שכירות *kach schirus* also borrowing
it, the lease works through money, a money
contract and חזקה *chazaka*. שכירות מאי עבידתיה *schirus mai avidtei*? What do
you why are we talking about שכירות *schirus*? Why are we talking
about borrowing an object? We're not talking about borrowing an object. אמר
רב חסדא *amar Rav Chisda* שכירות קרקע *schirus karka*. We're talking about
borrowing land.
Borrowing land? Yes.
Okay. That's enough of that for the moment. Now we're going to
have two סוגיות *sugyas* about Shmuel's opinions about what I'm liable for
when I steal or damage something.
And this is still getting into מעילה *me'ila*. So we moved into
the we brought מעילה *me'ila* into the discussion to deal with seeing
how the קנין *kinyan* works to create an obligation. מעילה *me'ila* was
a good test for that. And now we're going to continue talking
about מעילה *me'ila* a little bit in the way it plays out
in other cases
and how it how it's different slightly, it's obviously dealt with more
in מסכת מעילה *Masechet Me'ila*. But here we're just going to see
a couple of cases where מעילה *me'ila* turns is importantly different from
normal ownership.
Right, in other words, if you clar- if you clarified that the
law in some case is that there was מעילה *me'ila*, then you
could try to figure out how did it get into the person's
רשות *reshus* such that they were over the מעילה *me'ila*? Right.
Now the problem is whether we can learn from מעילה *me'ila* because
מעילה *me'ila* we're going to see is a much stricter rule.
Right, it's like going from the okay. Okay, back to the שכירות
קרקע *schirus karka* thing.
So if you give me the keys, it doesn't do anything, right?
That's what we just read because
giving me the keys does do things. Why? I thought וכשם וכשם
*ucheshem ucheshem* וכשם שקרקע נקנית בכסף בשטר ובחזקה *ucheshem shekarka nikne b'kesef
b'shtar u'v'chazaka* once I have a חזקה *chazaka* of ownership, okay, כך
שכירות נקנית בכסף בשטר ובחזקה *kach schirus nikne b'kesef b'shtar u'v'chazaka*. Same
rules. Right. So where do we see the keys?
What? בכסף *b'kesef* is if I pay you money for it, the
שטר *shtar* is you know we have a contract that I rent
it.
Literally, you just gave me the keys, that wouldn't work. Some say
it would create the that creates the חיוב *chiyuv* of בדיקת חמץ
*bedikas chametz* on פסח *Pesach*, right, but that's a special case.
Right. So it doesn't mean so it's not giving me the keys.
No. It's not literally giving me the keys. If you want to
bring in a fourth case, bringing in a keys, that doesn't work.
Right, okay.
You have to actually be there.
That's what
a חזקה *chazaka* is. Okay. אמר
שמואל Shmuel
*amar Shmuel*...
if I can give him the money or I can give him
the keys... yeah. But see that's true. The problems here it's like
why is money not working properly, מעות קונות אפילו מדאורייתא *ma'os konot
afilu mid'oraisa*? Money should work even on a דאורייתא *d'oraisa* level. Why
is this only working under דרבנן *d'rabbanan* level? A little bit strange,
but we're not dealing with that right now. אמר שמואל Shmuel האי
מאן דגזל חביתא chavita, דתמרי מחבריה ואית בה חמישין תמרי אגב הדדי
מזדבנין בחמישין נכי חדא chada חדא chada חדא מזדבנן בחמישין *amar Shmuel:
Hai man d'gazal chavita d'tamrei mechavreih, v'is ba chamishin tamrei agav hadadei
mizdabnin b'chamishin naki chada, chada chada mizdabnan b'chamishin*. If I if someone
steals a big pack of dates from somebody else, Reuven steals a
pack of dates from Shimon. They're all packed together. And there are
50 dates in this giant pack. And if I sell the entire
pack of dates, I sell if I sell them wholesale, then they're
worth 49 shekel, then they're worth 49 units. If I sell them
one at a time, they're worth 50.
So apparently, you get the bulk volume discount.
Not a great discount.
It's like just over a 2% discount. להדיוט l'hedyot משלם meshalem חמישין
נכי חדא *lehediot
meshalem chamishin naki chada*,
if I stole it from a normal person, then I pay back
the 49. להקדש משלם חמישין וחומשו *lehekdesh meshalem chamishin v'chomsho*, but for
הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh* I pay back the full amount plus the חומש
*chomesh* that I owe הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* for mis- for misappropriation. מה
שאין כן במזיק דלא
משלם חומשא *mah she'ein ken b'mazik d'lo meshalem chomsha*, what's not the
case for if I damage the property of הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* where
I don't actually pay the חומשא *chomsha*, I don't pay the extra
fifth for misappropriating because I didn't misappropriate, I just damaged temple property.
דאמר מר *de'amar mar* because we have the source that makes this
point explicitly
in a number of places, as you'll see on the side, it
cites all the places where it says: איש כי יאכל yochal קדש
*ish ki yochal kodesh* פרט למזיק prat l'mazik, *prat lemazik*, that when
we have the the when the Torah says person who eats improperly
holy sacred food, in this case it's actually talking about תרומה trumah
*trumah*, but תוספות *Tosafot* explains that there's a גזירה שוה *gezeira shava*
that makes תרומה *trumah* the same as הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*, which is
why we're talking about... and we're talking about הקדש hekdesh here. פרט
למזיק, that יאכל in the פסוק, pasuk, eating, excludes damaging. So the
use of the use of the temple property or the use of
תרומה in the actual פסוק pasuk
means use, not damaging. So damaging the temple property we've established doesn't
pay the חומש, that's just a side note here. מתיבי metivei ביבי
בר אביי Bibi bar Abaye להדיוט אמאי משלם חמשה chamishah כחדא. k'echada.
נימא ליה neima lei אנא ana חדא חדא הוה hava מזבנינא mazbeinu
להו lahu אבא aba מזבנינא mazbeinu להו. lahu. Why why just in
a סתם, stam,
why just in any case do when I steal from a normal
person, do I always pay that person back the lower amount as
if I'd sold the giant pack of dates at wholesale price? Why
can't the person who was stolen from say, I don't sell wholesale,
I sell retail. You owe me the extra shekel, the extra date.
You owe me the value of the extra date as if you'd
sold them one by one. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע
Amar Rav Huna
brei d'Rav
Yehoshua בשמין בית
סאה באותה שדה תנן.
bishamin
beit se'ah b'oto sadeh t'nan.
Now
that's when we're talking about damaging, loss of part of it, we
actually we don't do the specific loss that you had for your
thing. If my cattle enters your field and eats part of it,
I don't say, oh, how much did those ears of corn, did
that wheat, what was the value of that wheat? We assess the
damage to the entire field. So we take and the damage to
the entire field is much less on the large scale than on
the small scale.
Right, it's always, right, right, right, it always costs less to buy
something in bigger quantity.
Not that much less apparently here. Okay.
Well, that sums that up. Also I love the fact that he
stole from his friend. אנא חברי, ana chavrei, I don't know, anyway.
Okay.
למימר L'meimar דסבר d'savar שמואל Shmuel דין הדיוט din hedyot לאו כדין
lav k'din גבוה gavoh דמי? dami? Is this to say so שמואל
Shmuel has a distinction between דין הדיוט din hedyot from stealing from
a normal person and stealing from גבוה, gavoh, stealing from the most
high, which in our case is stealing from the temple property.
Does he think that they're different? But we have another source ותנן
vatnan נטל אבן או קורה מהקדש לא מעל. natal even o korah
mehekdesh lo maal. If I steal a stone or a wooden beam
from temple property, לא מעל. lo maal. I haven't yet done מעילה.
I haven't yet misappropriated the temple property because I've just taken it.
נתנה לחבירו n'sana l'chavero הוא מעל hu maal וחבירו לא מעל. v'chavoro
lo maal. If I give it to my friend, that's my, that's
already מעילה on my part, but it's not yet מעילה on the
part of my friend. My friend hasn't yet misappropriated even though I
have.
ובנה בתוך ביתו, u'vna b'toch beiso, if my friend takes the beam
that I stole from temple property and I gave to him and
he built it into his house,
לא מעל עד שידור תחתיה בשוה פרוטה. lo maal ad sheyadur tachtea
b'shaveh perutah. He's not, he hasn't actually misappropriated of the property even
then, even though it's part of another building, until,
and this is the גזבר, gizbar, right?
That's why he yes, but
until he sat in the house where the sitting in the house
was the value of a פרוטה, perutah, was the minimum value that
I could measure. יתיב רב אבהו קמיה דרבי יוחנן ויתיב וקאמר משמיה
דשמואל
Yativ Rav Abbahu kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan v'yativ
v'ka'amar mishmei d'Shmuel זאת אומרת zot omeret הדר בחצר חבירו שלא מדעתו
צריך להעלות לו שכר. hadar b'chatzer chaveiro shelo mada'ato tzarich l'haalos lo
sachar.
רב אבהו Rav Abbahu has a tradition that he taught before רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in this case, that שמואל Shmuel says that our
source about taking the אבן או קורה, even o korah, taking the
stone or the beam from הקדש, hekdesh giving it to my friend,
my friend builds it into his house and he sits in the
house, this actually teaches us something about a הדיוט, hedyot, which implies
that the דין din are the same to some degree, apparently.
That it this teaches us if I'm living in my friend's, if
I spend some time in my friend's domain, in his field without
him knowing about it, I have to pay him for it.
So the so that הקדש שלא מדעת hekdesh shelo mada'at in this
case, I gave you temple property, you didn't know it was temple
property, you wouldn't have done anything with it if it was temple
property, you built it into your house, you stayed in it, that's
הקדש שלא מדעת. hekdesh shelo mada'at. הקדש שלא מדעת hekdesh shelo mada'at
teaches us about שאילה
שלא מדעת, she'ilah shelo mada'at, that if I borrow something from an
owner without the owner knowing something about it, in this case using
the field without the owner knowing know something about it.
Yes, there's something really basic I'm missing about מעילה. נטל natal אבן
even או קורה o korah מהקדש mehekdesh לא מעל.
lo maal.
But
I'm
touching, I'm like I'm getting some הנאה hana'ah from it let's say.
it feels good.
You know what I'm saying? It's like I'm straddling a horse of
הקדש hekdesh and I rub up against it. It's like this is
like a building block, you know?
I think we might say that that's not measurable. So remember that
we say עד שידור בו שוה פרוטה, ad sheyador bo shaveh perutah,
until you stay in it an amount that would be worth a
penny. So the הקדש, the value, the הנאה hana'ah, that I get,
the benefit I get just from having temple property, that isn't
misappropriated. So we saw we're talking about a person, we talked about
the person who has the actual הקדש, who has the axe that
belongs to the temple.
They weren't doing the מעילה until they lent it. There has to
be some real הנאה, hana'ah. a measurable,
quantifiable הנאה.
hana'ah Not so, certainly nothing that is symbolic or psychological because that's
not measurable, not even something that's potential. I took the actual הקדש.
I could therefore tomorrow chop down the rotten tree in my חצר,
chatzer, but I haven't used it yet is what you're saying.
Right.
Yeah.
Okay.
I just wonder if there's an underlying motivation of wanting to prevent
מעילה from actually happening as long as possible, like giving people a
chance to, at that point you can still return it back.
Right, yes.
I don't know all the rules of הקדש, there's probably something in
here that we're missing, but it's good to bring that up that
we're dealing with the measurable.
How exactly זאת אומרת? zot omeret?
How was this, what part of that was זאת אומרת? zot omeret?
So we talked about, so it's not, there isn't זאת אומרת. zot
omeret. This is a
שמואל Shmuel infers from the rule about the beam from temple property
that I'm not חייב in מעילה until I build it into the
house and spend time in the house, that's measurable, a measurable quantity
of הנאה from the beam in my house. This teaches us, he
infers from it, that the same is the case in שואל שלא
מדעת. sho'el she-lo mada'at. הקדש שלא מדעת hekdesh she-lo mada'at teaches us
שואל שלא מדעת. sho'el she-lo mada'at. And if that means that they
are the same, we should say that הקדש שלא מדעת hekdesh she-lo
mada'at is
or is even stricter. So why am I learning parallel? I should
be learning to the, to a different case.
How exactly זאת אומרת zot omeret is not clear and in fact
the next line of the גמרא Gemara is הדר ביה שמואל. hadar
beh Shmuel. Okay, fine. שמואל Shmuel doesn't actually hold
that, שמואל Shmuel changed his mind. And he doesn't hold that we
learn from הקדש שלא מדעת hekdesh she-lo mada'at a rule about שואל
שלא מדעת. sho'el she-lo mada'at. We don't learn from the misappropriation of
temple property without knowing that it's temple property a rule also about
borrowing from my friend without my friend knowing that I'm borrowing from
him.
But the reason why he did want to infer is because you
have to have a הנאה שווה פרוטה hana'ah shaveh pruta or something
like that? Yes. So therefore this guy has to have הנאה שווה
פרוטה. hana'ah shaveh pruta. Yes.
And that he's, and that he's liable when his friend doesn't know
about it. And הקדש שלא מדעת hekdesh she-lo mada'at is similar to
that or so we
assume
at that level, at that stage. ממאי דמהא הדר ביה, mimai de-me-ha
hadar beh, how do we know that it's this that he went
back on? דילמא מהא הדר ביה, dilma me-ha hadar beh, maybe he
went back on the thing about the pack of dates? Pack of
dates he treated הקדש and הדיוט hedyot differently. He treated temple property
and normal people property differently. Maybe he went back on that. So
apparently we have a tradition, two traditions of שמואל Shmuel that come
together and the end of that is הדר ביה שמואל. hadar beh
Shmuel. There's some contradiction in שמואל's Shmuel teachings. There's a contradiction in
שמואל's Shmuel teachings, he goes back on one of them.
We want to say that it's the second one, but there's no
actual proof within the tradition that it is the second teaching, that
it is the teaching that הקדש and הדיוט hedyot are the same.
Maybe it's the teaching that הקדש and הדיוט hedyot are different and
שמואל Shmuel actually does believe that temple property is treated the same
as normal people property.
Meaning we just know he went
back on one of them, changed his mind. How do we know
that it's the second one?
לא, מהא הדר ביה. lo, me-ha hadar beh. We reject that possibility,
we say it was definitely the second one. Why? כי דרבא, ki
de-Rava, דאמר רבא, de-amar Rava, הקדש שלא מדעת כהדיוט מדעת דמי, hekdesh
she-lo mada'at ke-hedyot mada'at dami, that literally the second point is wrong.
רבא Rava disagrees explicitly with the second source. The
second source was about the קורה של הקדש, kora shel hekdesh, the
beam from temple property that I put in my house and then
I'm חייב a minimum amount once I've lived in it a minimum
amount, is teaching me the case of שואל שלא מדעת, sho'el she-lo
mada'at, I'm living in my friend's חצר chatzer without my friend knowing
about it, we say no that's not, that's not how you learn.
You learn הקדש שלא מדעת. hekdesh she-lo mada'at. I have a beam
from temple property that I don't know is a beam from temple
property and I've gotten a minimum amount of benefit from it, that
teaches me about שואל מדעת sho'el mada'at that when am I liable
for borrowing, when my friend does know about it.
But that's רבא, Rava, I'm confused. How are we learning about שמואל
Shmuel from רבא? Rava?
Presumably שמואל Shmuel, only follows part of רבא. Rava.
And then we, so the גמרא Gemara asserts that שמואל holds like
רבא Rava because רבא Rava makes this claim and that claim makes
a lot of sense to us. We say that הקדש should be
a stricter rule. רש"י Rashi explains that why is הקדש a stricter
rule? Why is הקדש שלא מדעת hekdesh she-lo mada'at like what?
הקדש is always lenient.
Ah, there's a specific rule here. We're talking about הקדש שלא מדעת
hekdesh she-lo mada'at
and שאילה מדעת. she'ilah mada'at. We're talking about misappropriation of temple property
without knowing that it's temple property
and borrowing from my friend without him the owner knowing about it.
But God, who's the owner of the temple property, always knows where
God's property is.
And so that's why הקדש שלא מדעת Hekdesh she-lo mi-da'at רש"י Rashi
explains it should be the same as שאלה מדעת she'elah mi-da'at
or כהדיוט מדעת. ke-hedyot mi-da'at. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so now we're going to, we solved that, we have the two
statements of שמואל, we hold by the first one, not by the
second one.
Wait, did we answer though about the whole the dates, like how
do we know they're not going to sell them you know individually?
Did he get a discount?
הדיוט Hedyot is הדיוט hedyot is a lower level or we're more
lenient when you sell from a הדיוט. hedyot. Even
if I'm not,
even if I'm you know like the kind of guy that, I
mean should it depend if I'm like a wholesaler or a retailer,
no?
I don't know what to tell you.
I don't think so. Why not? Does that not make sense? That
would be a way to understand it. If I'm like you know,
if that's what I do, like I typically sell like little things
you know then I shouldn't be getting that.
I sold from a retailer.
If it depends if I'm Costco, which I'm selling in bulk, or
if I'm like you know some normal guy.
If I sold from a retailer I should be able to claim
back to you. No, I'm a retailer.
I think the answer was just because...
No, because that's the point, we just don't say that, we don't
care. Yeah, סמכינן אבתרא דביצא. samchinan abatra de-beiza.
When I, when I destroy part of your property, I treat it
as part of a larger amount that we have a lenient rule
when some of it is lost.
So it's just the way it is. Meaning it makes no difference
if you know even I always just sell little you know pieces
like one by one.
Yeah. I mean look at this, we're dealing with a case where
he has fifty dates and there's a two percent
price, there's a two point something percent price increase from wholesale to
retail. If we're dealing from wholesale to retail candy, does it matter
that? That's like a four hundred percent price increase.
So these are different, what we're thinking about wholesale and retail is
being something like that, being four hundred, being like it's four times
as much to buy one Hershey's bar than to buy the box
of Hershey's bars, each Hershey's bar is worth four times as much
when I buy it individually, and here each date is only worth
two percent more when I buy individually. So this is a very
different, the retail situation is very different.
Okay.
But the same
rule would
apply even today
based on this גמרא?
Gemara? Presumably. But I feel like that's, I don't know.
Do you feel like it's unfair?
It does feel unfair, so I don't actually know the rule.
And my question is like how we measure loss, right? I mean
the farmer or the field guy who's eaten also sells the crops
individually, right? Like in bulk, but we're basing it on the whole.
Is that, I don't know, something about it being more measurable or
something like that.
Okay, let's finish up the דף. daf.
Or maybe he would have lost it before he sold it or...
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הני שקולאי דתברו חביתא דחמרא דחננא ביומא דשוקא
מיזדבנא בחמשא ושאר יומי מיזדבנא בארבעא. hanei shakulay de-tabru chavita de-chamra de-chanana
be-yoma de-shuka mizdabna be-chamsha ve-sha'ar yomey mizdabna be-arba'a. Okay, a bunch of,
some carriers broke a barrel of wine that belonged to a wine
seller. On the day, on market day, it sells for five. The
rest of the week it sells for four. There's more demand on
the market day and so it has and so the price goes
up by twenty-five percent on the market day. So what do they
owe back?
So does it depend when they broke it?
Depends when they return it. אהדרו ליה ביומא דשוקא אהדרו ליה חביתא
דחמרא ושאר יומי אהדרו
ליה חמשא.
ahadro lei be-yoma de-shuka ahadro lei chavita de-chamra ve-sha'ar yomey
ahadro lei chamsha.
I thought they broke it. They broke it, it depends when they
give him back a thing. I broke your חביתא, chavita. I'm giving
you back a חביתא. chavita Okay. אהדרו ליה ביומא דשוקא אהדרו ליה
חביתא דחמרא ושאר יומי אהדרו ליה חמשא.
ahadro lei be-yoma de-shuka ahadro
lei chavita de-chamra ve-sha'ar yomey ahadro lei chamsha.
So the first thing is that if I'm giving it back to
you on the market day I give you back the חביתא chavita,
and the rest of the week I give you back the value
that it would be worth on the day of the market,
on the market day, the higher amount. ולא אמרן אלא דלא הוה
ליה חמרא לזבוני. ve-lo amran ela de-lo hava lei chamra le-zivuni. But
this only is the case if the wine seller whose חביתא, whose
barrel of wine was broken,
had
didn't have other wine to sell. And so then in that context
I'm liable for the higher amount of the of the barrel of
wine as it would be on the market day. אבל הוה ליה
חמרא לזבוני, aval hava lei chamra le-zivuni, if he had other wine
to sell and you broke my barrel of wine, האי איבעי ליה
לזבוני. hai ibai lei le-zivuni. Then he could have sold that, then
what's my great loss? Why am I owing him back the entire
value of the of the barrel of wine as it would be
on the market day? You should have sold other wine, I didn't
really lose, you didn't really lose five units on my account. ומנכית
ליה אגר טירחא ודמי ברזנייתא. u-manchit lei agar tircha u-dmei barzanyata.
And so we do conclude that if I that if I did
have other wine to sell I owe you less. ומנכית ליה אגר
טירחא ודמי ברזנייתא. u-manchit lei agar tircha u-dmei barzanyata.
And I take out the amount of the difficulty it was to
do something. I never really understood this. Tapping. The second one is
the tapping, it's the tapping of the barrel. There's another opinion that
it's meant that ברזנייתא barzanyata doesn't mean the tapping of the barrel,
that it actually means
the crier.
The crier? I don't know how they get that because ברזא, barza,
the crier saying I have wine to sell costs money, putting up
an ad. Advertising. Advertising.
But ברזא barza means the faucet. on the wine barrel and we
have a lot of discussions of wine faucet, apparently it's like a
serious thing.
Oh, like as in the word ברז. Berez.
Yes, ברזא. Barza. Putting a hole in a wine barrel properly is
a serious job, there are people whose job it is to put
holes in wine barrels, you have to pay them, which makes a
lot more sense to me than paying somebody to go around shouting.
So I don't know why, but wait, so that means I pay
you, I pay you less because I had to pay back for
that,
or I pay you also for the amount that it would cost
you to put the hole in the new
barrel?
I pay more, meaning I pay you five plus the cost. No,
מנכי ליה אגר טירחא ודמי ברזנייתא. Manki lei agar tirkha u-dmei barzanyata.
I subtract the amount of difficulty it was, the work I
put into it.
But why? Meaning, but if I broke your barrel which already had
a tap, then
shouldn't I pay you back a barrel with the already had the
tap? But I was already in your house. These are הני שקלאי,
Hani shaklai, people carrying the barrel for you. I carried the barrel,
I take that had some value, I subtract the value of my
work.
No, but I don't understand, if I carry a barrel which already
had a tap, why shouldn't I pay you back a barrel with
the already had the tap on it? What do I get to
deduct?
Well, then you're giving them back, I mean once you put the
tap in it only lasts a certain amount of time, right?
I tell you what, probably. I tell you what, what did I
miss? Maybe because it doesn't stay
in for that long.
Probably, yeah, but then it should say, it should make a difference
whether the barrel had a tap in it or not. And here
it doesn't seem to differentiate the original barrel that I
broke had a tap in it or not. You're right, which makes
me assume that the case that we're talking about in the original,
in the original one, so maybe you're right. Maybe it's the case
that if I had a barrel that had a tap in it
then I wouldn't pay you back for the amount of the tap,
and maybe it's the case that if I broke a barrel without
a tap in it I subtract the amount that it cost to
put the tap in. Or maybe it's not. We just saw that
it doesn't matter whether you're a wholesaler or a retailer. Exactly. That
it's like if I have to give you back a barrel then
I subtract the amount that it cost me to get the barrel
in working order for you to sell in the שוק. Shuk. Okay,
that's where we're stopping for today. We finished the entire דף. Daf.
Why does the advertising-